Guide to the Elihu Geer Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Elihu Geer collection
1827-1881
MS 1405
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.5
(16 boxes)
The collection consists of cashbooks, correspondence, daybooks, invoices, journals, ledgers and other materials documenting the financial operations of Elihu Geer's printing shop and stationery business in Hartford, Connecticut. Material relating to his publication of the Hartford Journal and the Congregationalist is also included in the collection.
Geer, Elihu, 1817-1887
Arrangement
Arranged by record type.
Scope and Contents
The Elihu Geer Collection consists of cashbooks, correspondence, daybooks, invoices, journals, ledgers, and other materials, documenting the financial operation of Elihu Geer's printing and stationery businesses in Hartford, Connecticut. The bulk of material dates from 1838, when Geer founded his printing establishment, to 1864. Material relating to the publication of the Congregationalist and the Hartford Journal, a pro-Whig daily, is included in the collection.
The various account books are arranged by record type and detail the growth of Geer's printing business from its beginnings. Daybooks, cashbooks, and journals trace daily income from printing and advertising and expenditures for papers, ink, other supplies, and labor, while ledgers record accounts with individual customers and suppliers. There are job books, which detail printing orders and prices and workmen's books, which detail accounts with journeymen, apprentices, agents, and carriers. There are also three bound volumes of mounted invoices for stock in the printing office and stationery store and regular inventories of store stock and printing supplies. Invoices often are on illustrated letterheads from wholesalers in New York, Boston, and London. Registers of bills payable and receivable record Geer's financial obligations and loans, while the yearly trial balances in folder 20 summarize the progress of business development through profit and indebtedness statements.
The correspondence relates primarily to the establishment and operation of the Hartford Journal. Copies of Geer's outgoing letters are in cashbook B (folder 4) and in his letterbook (folder 38). The letterbook copies are in faint handwriting, some are also in Geer's shorthand. (Folder 53 contains a notebook of Geer's shorthand symbols.) For the newspaper and the Congregationalist there are also lists of subscribers by location and alphabetically arranged accounts. These lists also detail arrangements for the distribution of the papers.
Among the other materials in the collection are a few early items including an unidentified cashbook of the late 1820s (folder 54) and Geer's own notebook from his study of double entry bookkeeping at E. Perkins school (folder 46). Printing samples, such as circulars, letterhead stationery and forms, and catalogs, from Geer's printing office are in folder 47, and a sample book of typeface styles is in folder 52. Materials after 1864 for Geer's business interests are very fragmentary. Folder 48 contains a receipt book for domestic and personal expenses from 1862 to 1875. All receipts are from Hadlyme, Connecticut.
The Elihu Geer Collection in 1985.
Biographical / Historical
Elihu Geer was a printer and publisher in Hartford, Connecticut. He operated a printing shop and stationery store. Geer also published the Hartford Journal from 1843-1844 and Geer's Hartford Directory.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Hartford Journal; Business; Printing; Stationery trade; Connecticut -- Commerce; Hartford (Conn.) -- Commerce; Account books; Inventories; Invoices; Ledgers; Printers; Geer, Elihu, 1817-1887
- Inventory, 1827-1881; 7.5 linear feet (16 boxes)
  - Bills payable register, 1841-1845
    General
    See: box 1, folder 1
  - Bills payable and receivable register, 1845-1858 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Workmen's book, 1841-1843
    See: box 12, folder 43
  - Workmen's book, 1843-1863 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cashbook, 1838-1839 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cashbook 'B', with copies of outgoing letters, 1842-1843, 1840-1843 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cash account journal, 1843-1846 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cashbook 'C', 1843-1847 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cashbook 'D', 1847-1852 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cashbook 'E', 1856-1865
    See: box 15, folder 57
  - Cashbook, 1859-1861 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1832-1852 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
    See also: box 11 folder 38
    See also: box 1, folder 4
  - Daybook, 1838-1839
    See: box 12, folder 45
  - Daybook 'C', 1838-1846 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Daybook for Printing Office", 1838-1850 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Daybook, advertising for the Congregationalist, 1839-1841 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Daybook 'D', 1847-1851 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Daybook, fragment, 1861-1862 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Directory mark up book, 1881 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "Inventory of paper cards, etc.", 1842-1850 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Inventories, store, 1851-1853, 1855 (Box 5, Folder 18-19)
  - "Inventories and Yearly Balances A, B, C, D, E", 1839-1850 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Invoices, 1850
    See: box 13, folder 51
  - Invoices, 1851-1853 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Invoice book 'C', 1854-1855 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Job books, 1841-1844 (Box 8, Folder 23-24)
  - Job book, 1845-1846
    See: box 12, folder 44
  - Job books, 1847-1851 (Box 8, Folder 25-26)
  - Journal 'E', store, 1852-1856 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Journal 'E', office, 1852-1856 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Journal 'F', store, 1856-1861 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Journal 'F', office, with cash journal of the Hartford Steam Printing Co., 1862-1863, 1856-1864 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - No folder (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Ledger, general, 1838-1839 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Ledger, for printing office materials, 1838-1844 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Ledger, Congregationalist, No. 1, 1839 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Ledger, 1843-1845 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Ledger, general 'C', with index, 1843-1846 (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - Ledger, general 'E', with index, 1852-1856 (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Ledger, general 'F', 1856-1870
    See: box 16, folder 58
  - Letterbook, 1843-1844 (Box 11, Folder 38)
  - List of subscribers, 1843-1844 (Box 12, Folder 39-41)
    See also: box 14, folders 55-56
  - General papers, 1864, 1881, undated (Box 12, Folder 42)
  - Wages ledger for journeymen, apprentices, and carriers, 1841-1842 (Box 12, Folder 43)
    See also: box 1, folder 2
  - Job book, 1845-1846 (Box 12, Folder 44)
    See also: box 8, folders 23-26
  - Daybook, fragment, 1838-1839 (Box 12, Folder 45)
  - Student bookkeeping notebook, 1836-1837 (Box 12, Folder 46)
  - Printing samples book, [ca. 1840-1860] (Box 12, Folder 47)
  - Receipt book, personal and domestic, 1862-1875 (Box 12, Folder 48)
  - Bills payable register, 1841-1845 (Box 13, Folder 49)
    See also: box 1, folder 1
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 13, Folder 50)
  - Invoices, 1850 (Box 13, Folder 51)
    See also:box 6, folders 21-22
  - Typeface sample book, undated (Box 13, Folder 52)
  - Shorthand symbols notebook, 1843 (Box 13, Folder 53)
  - Oversize
    - Cashbook, 1827-1831 (Box 14, Folder 54)
    - Subscribers' lists, 1843-1844 (Box 14, Folder 55-56)
    - Cashbook 'F', 1856-1865 (Box 15, Folder 57)
    - Ledger, general 'F', with index, 1856-1870 (Box 16, Folder 58)